<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dolorous discourse, of a most terrible and bloudy battel, fought in Barbarie, the fowrth day of August, last past. 1578 VVherein were slaine, two kings, (but as most men say) three, besyde many of her famous personages: with a great number of captains, and other souldiers that were slaine on both sides. VVhereunto is also annexed, a note of the names of diuerse that were taken prisoners at the same time.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108235</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843907</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 171:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dolorous discourse, of a most terrible and bloudy battel, fought in Barbarie, the fowrth day of August, last past. 1578 VVherein were slaine, two kings, (but as most men say) three, besyde many of her famous personages: with a great number of captains, and other souldiers that were slaine on both sides. VVhereunto is also annexed, a note of the names of diuerse that were taken prisoners at the same time.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Charlewood, and Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1579]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Africa, North --  History --  1517-1882 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶<hi>A Dolorous diſcourſe, of <hi>a moſt terrible and bloudy</hi> Battel, fought in Barbarie, the</hi> fowrth day of Auguſt, laſt paſt. 1578.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>herein were ſlaine, two Kings, (but as moſt then ſay) three, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde many <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>mous perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umber of Captains, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Souldiers that were <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ine on both ſides.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is alſo annexed, a note</hi> of the names of diuerſe that were taken priſoners at the ſame time.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Charlwood, consisting of the arms of the city of Geneva (divided vertically into two equal parts and showing the left half of the imperial eagle and a key of St. Peter) first used by Rowland Hall in Geneva in 1562-53 and passed to John Charlwood at an unknown date (McKerrow)</figDesc>
               <q xml:lang="lat">POST TENEBRAS LVX</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> abonde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> great reaſon, (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader,) that the auncient Poets in old time; fained <hi>Phaeton</hi> to fal from heauen, and to be drowned in the deapth of the Sea: becauſe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his calling, he woulde of a prowde ambicious minde, preſume to take vppon him the gouernement of his Father <hi>Phaebus</hi> Chariot, being a thing farre beyond his ſkil to compas. For ſurely there is not in the whole world, a more peſtilent euil, or a thing that breedeth ſo much miſchife, as doth the cankred and moſt accurſed vice of ambition, which not onely worketh the ruine of the partye therewith poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſed: but often times cauſeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of many mighty Monark<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and
<pb facs="tcp:8672:3"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e vtter ouerthrovv of whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes and common weales.</p>
            <p>Wherewith the words of <hi>Cornelius <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>rus</hi> do verry aptly agree, who ſaith that after the deſier of principallytie had longe continued in the mindes of men vndiſcouered: when Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an to enlarge their Limittes, and to make their dominions greater: when they began to conquer kingdomes, and enuying the felicitie of common weales, deſired the confuſion and vtter ouerthrowe one of another. Then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan this ambition firſt of all to breake out, which as (Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaieth) pleaſeth and delighteth euery man, and yet is there nothinge that doth more cruelly crucifie or breede more vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes, then it doth.</p>
            <p>For from whence ſpringeth bloody warres ſo much, as from this roote of Ambition.</p>
            <p>What cauſeth ſo manye to endure the extremitie of the coulde Winter nightes, by lying abroade in the open
<pb facs="tcp:8672:3"/> Feeldes without any harbour, and to abide the heate of the whot Sommer ſeaſon being clogged with the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of their vnweldye armoure: but onelye ambicion?</p>
            <p>Is it ought els but this greedy ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that maketh men to trauell ſo many intemperate countryes, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately to runne into ſo many doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full daingers as they do?</p>
            <p>In concluſion, there is nothing that more breaketh the bandes of beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, abateth the obedience of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towardes their Parentes: the loue of Parentes, towardes their Children: the dutye of ſubiectes, towardes their Princes, and the care of Countryes commoditye, from al men, as doth this abominable vice of ambicion.</p>
            <p>Whereof dyuers hiſtoryes aſwell of auncient time, as examples daylye ſhewed amongſt vs, is a moſt perfect teſtimony.</p>
            <p>By the greedye ambition of <hi>Scilla Marius, Carbo, Cinna, Pompeius,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:4"/> there were more ſlaine amongſt the <hi>Romaines,</hi> then in conquering to them the kingdome of the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silla</hi> condempned &amp; cauſed to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted 80000. <hi>Romaines,</hi> beſydes many <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore that were ſlaine in the ciuil wars, betweene him and both the <hi>Marius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Pompeius</hi> and <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> the one ſuffring no peere, the other no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, by their inſaſiable ambition, cauſed innumerable people to be ſlaine betweene them, and ſubuerted the beſt and moſt renowmed publique weale, in the whole world: and finally, enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little time to reioyce them in theyr vnlawfull deſires, <hi>Pompeius</hi> ſhamefullye flyinge, had his head ſtroken off, by the commaundement of <hi>Ptolome</hi> Kinge of <hi>Egipt:</hi> vnto whom as to his frende he fled for ſuccour, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> that was the vanquiſher, was ſhortlye after cruellye murdred in the Senate, with daggers, by them whom he beſt truſted, and moſt ſpecially fauowred.</p>
            <p>It would require much time, and a
<pb facs="tcp:8672:4"/> verye large volume, to make mencion of all thoſe that heretofore, by coueting to encreaſe their credit and eſtimation in the worlde, and to aduaunce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to high dignities, haue brought both themſelues and their countryes to extreame daunger.</p>
            <p>But I will leaue heere to rehearſe any more of ſuch antiquitye, and ſhew a more liuely &amp; lamentable example, of three renowmed Princes: who not longe ſince by their ambicious deſires, did not onely procure their owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death: but alſo the deſtruction of many thouſandes of their people, in the maintenaunce of their vniuſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, as by that which followeth ſhall more manifeſtly appeare.</p>
            <p>But before I proceede to the matter, I haue here thought good, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders better inſtruction, breflye to diſcribe the country of <hi>Barbary,</hi> and the cuſtomes thereof.</p>
            <p>(⸪)</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:5"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A diſcription of the orders and cuſtomes of Barbary.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Arbary, is a country</hi> ſcituate in <hi>Affrica,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited with a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous people obſeruinge the lawes of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> geuen (for the moſt part) to idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; ſundry ſuperſticions.</p>
               <p>In this Countrye are manie <hi>Iewes</hi> enhabiting, in whoſe handes conſiſteth the moſt parte of the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique of the Country, being the onelye Marchantes of Sugers, Mallaſſes, and other ritche marchandize which the ſame yeldeth: for the which, they paye great ſums of money to the king. And now to the matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:5"/>
               <head>¶<hi>A Dolorous diſcourſe of a moſt terrible blouddy Battell fought in Barbarie the.</hi> 4. <hi>of Auguſt.</hi> 1578.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderſtande, that not long ſynce, there raygned ouer the countrey of <hi>Barbary,</hi> a King named <hi>Mully Hamet Shek<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> who had diuers Sons by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry his Wiues and Concubines: for there they maye haue as manye wiues as they wyll.</p>
               <p>The King paſſing on a tyme from <hi>Moroccus,</hi> the chiefe City of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, towards another Countrey of his, called <hi>Sus,</hi> was in the mydway, at a place called <hi>Bibon,</hi> murdred by his owne men.</p>
               <p>After him raigned one of his Sons called <hi>Mulla Abdula:</hi> by whoſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes a Noble man of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countrey, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Alcatho Alley,</hi> cauſed the throtes of eleuen of the Kinges Brethren, to be cutte in one morning.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:6"/>
               <p> Two other of his brethren fled for feare into Turky, and were there brought vp in the <hi>Turks</hi> warres.</p>
               <p>One other of his Brethren named <hi>Mulla Hamet,</hi> remayned ſtyll in <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary,</hi> without any violence offered vnto him, and was well beloued of his wicked brother: ſo that he grew verye rytch, and was in great eſtimation throughout the whole countrey.</p>
               <p>And as cruel murder can neuer lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g reſt vnrewarded. This <hi>Alkatho Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> the onely miniſter of the Kinges miſchieuous deuiſe, was in the ende meaſured with ſuch a lyke meaſure, as he had before meat to the Kings brethren.</p>
               <p>Now the cruel king <hi>Mulla Abdula:</hi> amongſt manye other, taking to his wife a bond woman, that was a <hi>Blacke Negro,</hi> had by her a ſonne, called <hi>Mulla Sheriffa:</hi> who for that he was of his Mothers complection, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called the <hi>Black King,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8672:6"/> to whome <hi>Mulla Abdula</hi> his Father commytted the kingdome after his death, as to his onely heyre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulla Hamet,</hi> after the death of his brother <hi>Abdula,</hi> fearing the tyranny of his Blacke Neuew that ſucceded him, fled incontinently with all his ſubſtaunce and treaſure, to <hi>Argere,</hi> a Towne belonging to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Turke,</hi> wher he remayned in good ſafetie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulla Sheriffa,</hi> hauing for a whyle peaceably poſſeſſed the Crowne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came in the ende ſo cruel a tyrant, as his people therfore hating him, mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mured in their mindes at his great ſeuerity, and in the ende burſt out in plaine ſpeches, ſaying: that the ſonne of a bond woman ſhould not raigne ouer them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulla Hamet,</hi> his Vncle, remaining all this whyle at <hi>Argere,</hi> &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding how the people were enclined, by the procurement of the moſt part of the Nobility of the Realme: ſent to his Brother <hi>Mulla Maluca,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:8672:7"/> remayned with the <hi>Turke,</hi> wylling him with all expedition, to procure ſuch forces as he coulde, &amp; to returne therwith into the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try of <hi>Barbary,</hi> where he certifyed him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhoulde be ſure to finde ſuch friendes as hee might eaſely attaine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crowne.</p>
               <p>With this good hope, <hi>Mulla Malu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> hauing obtayned of the <hi>Turke</hi> (in recompence of his long ſeruice with him) a band of. 10000. <hi>Turks.</hi> He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with them into <hi>Barbary,</hi> where hee was wyllingly receyued by his friends and fauourers, and greatlie ſuccoured, aſwel by them, as with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtaunce of his brother <hi>Mulla Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> who ſpared nothing to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him with all, or to further his preſent enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulla Sheriffa,</hi> his Black Nephew, vnderſtanding of his comming: Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied a huge Army, to make reſpſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt him: but yet although his power farre ſurmounted the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of his enemies, yea: though hee had
<pb facs="tcp:8672:7"/> ten to one, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Vncle <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la Maluca:</hi> Yet what through his owne valliancie, and the good wyll that he knewe the common people bare to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulla Maluca,</hi> dyd in ſhort tyme ſo preuaile againſt the ſayd <hi>Sheriffa,</hi> as dryuing him to the Mountaynes of the countrey, he obteyned poſſeſſion of the Crowne, and euer ſynce hath continued king of <hi>Barbary:</hi> where he was well beloued of his people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man very actyue, and of great agillitie, ſkylfull in warres, wherein from his youth he had alwayes ben trayned vp: and as men report, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred Iuſtice with equitie, much fauouring Chriſtians, and ſpecialie our Nation.</p>
               <p>The Blacke king, when he fled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mountaynes, carryed with him a great parte of the Treaſure of the Countrey, and dayly dyſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the quyet poſſeſſion of his Vncle <hi>Maluca.</hi> Who ſlepte not in the
<pb facs="tcp:8672:8"/> meane ſpace: but prepared by all meanes to preuent whatſoeuer his Blacke Nephew myght doo to his preiudice. And in the ende, draue him to ſo great extremitie, that he was forced to craue ayde of the king of <hi>Portingale:</hi> who hath certayne holdes in that countrey.</p>
               <p>The Kinge of <hi>Portingale</hi> being a luſty young Gentleman, about. xxiij. yeares of age, peraduenture pricked forwarde by a vaine hope and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſire of gaine and glory, not reſpecting the perril y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ther vppon: promiſed the ſayd <hi>Sheriffa</hi> to performe his deſyre therein. And thereupon leuied an Armye, to the number of. 40000. in all: to wete 16000. <hi>Portingale</hi> footemenne, and 4000. horſemen. 10000. footemen of <hi>Spaniards,</hi> high <hi>Almaines</hi> and <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians,</hi> and. 10000. that were Pages, Seruauntes, Purueiours, and ſuch lyke continuallye accompaning the Campe. With this power the king
<pb facs="tcp:8672:8"/> of <hi>Portingale</hi> in his owne perſon<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> accompanied with a great number of his Nobillitie, departed out of his owne countrey on the .xiiii. day of <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1578. and with his whole fleete firſt ariued at a town in <hi>Spaine</hi> called <hi>Calez:</hi> where he made his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of. viij. whole dayes together, the occaſion whereof was, (as ſome ſuppoſe) to furninſh his Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye with all ſuch things, as ſhould be needefull for the proſecution of his pretenſed purpoſe.</p>
               <p>And on the. 22. daye of the foreſayd month of Iuly, he gathered his men together, and with all expedition paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Calez,</hi> to another Towne lying within the bord<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> called <hi>Tanos:</hi> where hee mett<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the Blacke Kings, who had with him, fyue hundreth <hi>Mores</hi> Horſemen. And after he had alſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourned therefor a ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he departed from thence to <hi>Argele:</hi> Which is a certayne Houlde that the ſayde king
<pb facs="tcp:8672:9"/> of <hi>Portingale</hi> hath in <hi>Barbary,</hi> and after his departure from thence.</p>
               <p>The fyrſt daye, which was the. 29 day of the ſayd Iuly: the ſayd king of <hi>Portingale</hi> with his whole power, marched forward one League far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which is three of our Engliſhe miles, &amp; pitched his Tents in a place called <hi>Sweete Riuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond day, he went forward one League more, and in that place remained for the ſpace of two whole dayes. In which tyme there was diſcouered on the toppe of a verye high hil, a troope of Horſemen of the <hi>Mores,</hi> which wereby eſtimation, not aboue the number of. 400. in the whole, and the cauſe of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as it might very well be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, was onelye to take a view of the king of <hi>Portingales</hi> Campe, to know of what power he was: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che indeede ſtandeth greatlye with reaſon, for that after their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, they departed againe ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainlye
<pb facs="tcp:8672:9"/> without <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or making any other<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The third day of y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> proceeding, he marche<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leagues farder, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance quietly pitched hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto a Ryuer called <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> remayned all that night.</p>
               <p>The. 4. day he alſo m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> furder, &amp; arriued at a City of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, called <hi>Alcaſar Kiber,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ich City &amp; them, ran the great <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> and the bridge therof was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye garded by. 2000. <hi>Mores</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>en: that the king of <hi>Portingale</hi> per<gap reason="illegible" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>g it to be impoſſible without <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to paſſe that way: becauſe he w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>re his men tyl more meet<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght be offred for the proſecution of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enterpriſe: he c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ed the contrey to finde out ſome otherwaye mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t for his purpoſe. And at th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lengt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me to a lytle Foorde whe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r his whole Army his Ordinance, &amp; carriages, without any d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t al, which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8672:10"/> worke, he was conſtrayned to harbor there all that night.</p>
               <p>The next daye the king of <hi>Portingale</hi> called all his moſt wyſe &amp; beſt experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Captaines to counſell, &amp; aſked theyr aduiſe: whether it were better for him with his whole power to martche to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde <hi>Alcaſany:</hi> which being a drye Towne, though there were in it about the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of. 7000. houſholds, yet was it but weake, vnmeete to make any great encounter, and not able long to ſtand in reſyſtaunce.</p>
               <p>Or elſe to proceede forewarde on his waye towards the Towne <hi>Alcaſar Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> before named.</p>
               <p>This being long debated betweene them, euerie man alleadging what he lyſted: After they had all particularly expreſſed their opinions therin, ſom one way, and ſome another way: in the end it was concluded with a general conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he ſhould keepe his courſe toward <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lcaſar Kiber,</hi> which he performed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dingly.</p>
               <p>He had not paſſed very farre before he
<pb facs="tcp:8672:10"/> diſcouered <hi>Mulla Maluca,</hi> that was king of <hi>Barbary,</hi> martching toword<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s him with a great power of men, which were valued to be in number. 70000. Horſemen, &amp;. 40000. Footemen, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. 20000. were Horſemen ſhotte, and 10000. Footemen gunners, beſydes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther followers of the campe: whoſe nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I haue not heard, and therfore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make a true report thereof.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the day was quite ſpent before the two Armyes could com<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y thing neere together, they both <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ped them ſelues there that night, in ſyght the one of the other.</p>
               <p>The next daye, being the fowrth of Auguſt. 1578. the King of <hi>Portingale</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided his battel into fowre ſqu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>drons: whereof he appoynted to <hi>Don Duer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>e Menneſſes,</hi> Generall of the Army, the leading of the Vautg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rde. The ſecond Squadron, the king <hi>Portingale</hi> himſelf tooke charge off. Vpon the right hande was the Blacke king <hi>Sheriffa,</hi> with his Horſemen: And vpon the left hande; the Duke <hi>Dauerro,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of the
<pb facs="tcp:8672:11"/> Duke of <hi>Barganſy,</hi> with the. 4. Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Maluca,</hi> dyd alſo vſe the lyke other in the deuiſion of his Army.</p>
               <p>All thinges being thus prepared on both ſydes, the two Kinges purpoſyng to put themſelues to the hazarde of that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich ſhoulde happen, adreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to fight.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Maluca,</hi> fyrſt gaue the Onfette vpon the Horſemen of the <hi>Portingales</hi> Armye, but they vallyauntly defended them ſelues, and in the ende forced <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> and his <hi>Mores,</hi> to retyre with the loiſe of many of them.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Maluca</hi> herewith nothing dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, bringing his men agayne in good order of Battell: gaue ſuch a freſh charge vppon the Kyng of <hi>Portingales</hi> Horſemen, as he conſtrained them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre vnto the mayne battell.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Portingales</hi> Horſemen, being <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncontinently gathered againe together <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n good order, they gaue the <hi>Mores</hi> ſuch <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſharpe charge, that they flewe a great
<pb facs="tcp:8672:11"/> number of them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mores</hi> agayne returned freſhly vppon the forces of the <hi>Portingale</hi> horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, forcing them to ioygne with theyr footemen.</p>
               <p>Which done, the ſayde <hi>Portyngales</hi> gaue a newe chardge vpon the <hi>Mores:</hi> But theyr beſt Souldiors beyng ſlayne before, and hauing no newe ſuccourers, to ſupplye theyr wantes: for that they were farre from theyr friendes, and in a forrayne countrey, amongſt theyr mortall enemyes: whoſe power great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſurpaſſed theyrs, they were not able to doe any good at all.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Mores</hi> ſtyll remayning verye ſtronge, with the force of their Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhotte, and footemen Gunners, ſo brake the arrayes of the <hi>Portingale</hi> Horſemen, as they ouerthrewe, kylled, and tooke Captyue, the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, excepte. 80. or. 100. perſonnes at the moſt, that ſaued them ſelues by flight.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:12"/>
               <p> In this conflicte were ſlaine. 3000. <hi>Almaines.</hi> 700. <hi>Italians,</hi> and. 2000. <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>rds.</hi> whereof <hi>Don Allonſo Dageler</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>night of <hi>Cordua</hi> was one.</p>
               <p>In this laſt battel, it is ſuppoſed that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the three Kinges were ſlaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>
                              <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>he names of the Portingale Nobility, that were ſlaine.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Sabaſtian,</hi> Kinge of <hi>Portingale.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Lewis, de Cordua.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>on Diego de Menneſſes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>eorge de Silua</hi> Gouernoure and Iuſtice of Portingale.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Franciſco de Portingale.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Franciſco,</hi> ſonne to the Countye of Sortelha.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Conſtantino.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Ferdinando de Silua.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Allonſo de Almado.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Chriſtopher,</hi> and <hi>Don Auero</hi> Peeres of <hi>Trauora.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don Aluaro de Silua.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>More.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sheriffa</hi> the black Kinge.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:12"/>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>¶<hi>The names of ſuch as were taken, and are knowen to re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aine <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> in Barbary.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>THe Duke of <hi>Barganſas</hi> Sonne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Don Duart de Menneſſes,</hi> great <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter of the Campe, and Generall of the <hi>Tangere.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Don Farnando de Caſtra<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Controwler of the <hi>Fenances.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Don Diego de Silua.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Don Piedro de Menneſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>¶Diuerſe other Lordes and noble men there are miſſing, but whether they be ſlaine, or taken Captiues, it is not yet certainelye knowen.</p>
               <p>The dead body of the Kinge of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale</hi> is reported to rem<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n in <hi>Alc<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>r Kiber,</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delyuery wherof the <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> require in raunſome the townes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8672:13"/> 
                  <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ues</hi> and <hi>Arſylla,</hi> with the Munition therein.</p>
               <p>There is offered for the raunſome of the Duke of <hi>Barganſa</hi> his ſonne. 10000. Duccats: but it is refuſed.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Portingale</hi> loſt by this Battell. 22. peeces of Ordinaunce. 700. Chariottes, with Mules and Oxen: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes many other thinges of very great vallue.</p>
               <p>There were ſlayne of the <hi>Barbarians</hi> about the number of. 40. or. 50. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand one with another, whereof the King is ſuppoſed to be one.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Portingales</hi> haue choſen for their King, a Cardinall, that was great Uncle to their late King deſceaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:13"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>BEholde here, (gentle Read<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ende that greedy ambicion (<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> breedeth ſo many bloudy broyl<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bringeth them vnto, that imbrace <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Let the pittyfull ſpectacle here <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>downe to thy view: of the woful ad<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture that happened to the Princes <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſpoken off, by the confuſion of t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> people, and loſſe of theyr owne ly<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> ſerue thee as an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, (of what de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> ſo euer thou bee,) when thou feeleſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe prycked forward to the lyke en<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> priſe: by reaſon, to remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deuylliſh deſyre, which ſo greatly b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the vnderſtanding of many re<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable creatures, alluring them thro<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a conceyued hope of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which can n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> be compaſſed, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt things contr<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to all order &amp; honeſty: not regarding <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rewarde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ryghtfully belongeth to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſpyring mindes, nor the m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſerabl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of them that are ſo ambi<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uſly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Mulla Sheryffa,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Kynge here ſpoken off <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:14"/> was in quiet poſſeſſion of his kingdom, coulde haue gouerned his people with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ety, &amp; had not of a prowde ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mind, (to make his power appeare th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greater) So greuouſly oppreſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tyrany as he did: theyr loue towards him would haue ben ſuch, as his vncles <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>r ſhoulde neuer haue ſo preuayled <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>nſt him, as it dyd.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſayde <hi>Maluca</hi> coulde haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> him with the good eſtate he was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and had not lefte the ſeruice of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, (where he lyued peaceably, in <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eat honour and eſtimation,) to make himſelfe king of <hi>Barbary,</hi> by diſpoſſeſſing his Nephew of his ryghtfull enhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Portingale</hi> would neuer ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bene prouoked to make warres upon him, and to worke his confuſion, as he dyd.</p>
            <p>Finally, if the king of <hi>Portingale,</hi> had not of an ambicious minde, bene moued to enlarge his Dominions, with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loſſe, and to encreaſe his Fame by his raſhnes: in waging warres with th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſayde king <hi>Maluca,</hi> he ſhoulde not
<pb facs="tcp:8672:14"/> haue brought himſelfe, &amp; ſo many <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gentlemen, to that myſerable ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dyd, in a barborous countrey, amongſt a ſort of brutiſhe Infydelles: but might haue lyued in peace and great proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in his owne countrey, and haue ſtyll continued that commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which by his vertues and vallure he had woon &amp; well deſerued: whoſe lyke for wiſdome, courage, and good qualities (in ſuch young yeares) <hi>Portingale</hi> was neuer poſſeſſed withall before.</p>
            <p>And therefore all Chrinſtendome, but eſpecially the poore widdowes, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles chyldren, in <hi>Portingale,</hi> maye well with moſt pittifull complayntes, &amp; lamentable cryes, accompanied with floods of teares: be wayle, though all to late, the vnlucky lot of that vnfortunate Prince, and the dolefull daye, wherin vnaduiſedly, he fyrſt began this his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>O myſerable man, borne to woe and callamitie: was it not ſufficient that a thouſande thouſande miſchiefes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto thou waſt borne, ſhoulde fall vpon
<pb facs="tcp:8672:15"/> thee, and ouerwhelme thee in this vale of myſery: but that thou muſt by thyne owne vnkindly inclination, adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto murder, diſcorde, and deuiſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene countrey &amp; countrey, ſo careleſly: as thou doſt, contrary to the cuſtome of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll other earthly creatures of Gods cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating.</p>
            <p>What pleaſure haſt thou in the ſpoyle of thy people, O thou prowd and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions Prince? that to purchaſe to thy ſelf ſuch things as thou muſt leaue behynde thee, when God calleth thee away, out of this tranſitory worlde: wylt put ſo many in peryll of theyr life. When thou haſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attayned to thy inſatiable deſyre, thy mynde is neuer ſatiſfyed therwith, vn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yll thou thy ſelfe arte alſo become a pray to the woormes of the earth, or the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>es of the ayre.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall then remayne vnto thee, of all the ſpoyles and vyctories, that with the bloudſhed of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande men, thou haſt acquyred in thy whole lyfe tyme: ſurely nothing elſe but a ſyllye wynding ſheete, and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:8672:15"/> want that too, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> chaunce <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not the better.</p>
            <p>O Chriſtian Princes, imbrace peace, ſeeke to haue loue and amytie one with another, to the ſtrengthening, eſtably<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and enlarginge of Chriſtendome: leaſt the Infydelles, for the ſynnes of you and your people, be a ſcourge to you all.</p>
            <p>Hath not God by his infynite, and incomprehenſyble wiſedome, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye wrought in the placing of your Prouinces: euerye one with ſuch ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye commodityes, as the one ſhoulde alwayes haue neede of the other, to the ende that you ſhoulde lynke in Loue, and lyue in contynuall concorde, one wyth another? Yes verelye: And wherefore doo ye then alter the decree, and determynation of the Almyghtye: Who hath appoynted all theſe thynges for the benefyte of his people?</p>
            <p>O ye Subiectes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your hartye prayers, for peace and quietnes, and th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> continuance therof: that you with you<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiues, chyldren, friend<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8672:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> maye lyue quietly and peaceably toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mayntayning with your neceſſary trauayl, your countreys fertillitie, to the auoyding of penury, and the preuenting of ſuch lyke miſcheuous murders, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ſtly blouddy broyles, as are before ſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en of.</p>
            <p>O ye Prelates, Prophets, and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, if you be the Meſſengers and Miniſters of our Sauior Ieſus Chriſt: Preach to your Princes, and as Chriſt dyd, ſo do ye perſwade youthfull Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from ſeeking ſuch bloudy battels: ſo ſhall ye be knowne to be the Diſciples of that heauenly <hi>Meſsias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any perſwade Princes to the ſhedding of blood, murdring of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, and to make ſpoyle of the people, whome God hath onely created to his glory. They are not the ſeruauntes of Ieſus of Ieſus Chriſt: but in deede the very ſchoollers of Antichriſt, &amp; the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I woulde councell all men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of what calling ſo euer they be, as
<pb facs="tcp:8672:16"/> well Princes, as priuate <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſtie: them ſelues with that whiche <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhall pleaſe God to in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>te vnto the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: not ſeeking by vnlawful meanes, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunce them ſelues higher then GOD hath appointed, leaſt for their great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes, he do not onely diſapoynt them of their pretenſed purpoſe: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bereaue them of thoſe benefits, which before he had bountifully be ſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, which is the iuſt rewarde belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to ſuch vngratefull perſons.</p>
            <p>Surely if men woulde call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, the care, trouble, feare, &amp; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall daunger, that alwayes accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth thoſe that be aduaunced to highe dignities, and woulde <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aye with all, what aſſured ſafetie, con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>eth in the meane eſtate: I am full<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſwaded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e for promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as they dayly doo, nor ſeeke with ſuch inceſſaunt payne and peryll, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a thing ſo vnprofytable: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhunne it as a moſt peſtelent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl, being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only corrupter of good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp; vanquiſher of vertue, eſteeming
<pb facs="tcp:8672:17"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to lyue contented with a lytle: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeeking by diſhoneſt meanes to <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>haſe great abundance, to put both <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd body in daunger, the one of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ation, the other of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which enormities, the Lord for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mercies ſake delyuer vs: and make <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndfull of his manifold benefytes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtowed vpon vs: farre more ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then we can eyther deſyre, or <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>x ſuper omnia prodeſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>printed at London by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ohn Charlewood, and Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Man.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8672:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
